A Guide to the Waller Family Papers, 1737-1912
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Waller Family Papers, 1737-1912.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
DMS 54.6
1 volume and 35 items.
Waller Family.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1954.
Alternative Form
Also available on microfilm M-1555. Selected items available in transcription TR/80.
Biographical/Historical Information
Benjamin Waller was a lawyer and judge of Williamsburg Va. Some of his descendants were residents of Norfolk, Va.
Scope and Content Information
Papers associated with Benjamin Waller of Williamsburg and his descendants in Norfolk, Va. Included are appointments, 1737-1743, of Benjamin Waller as register of the Virginia Vice Admiralty Court, deputy clerk of James City County, king's attorney in Gloucester and James City counties, clerk of James City County, clerk of the Court of Oyer and Terminer, assistant clerk of the House of Burgesses, Clerk of the Committee of Propositions and Grievances, and Clerk of the Committee of Privileges and Elections; a deed, December 13, 1743, between Benjamin Waller and Mann Page, for the sale of land in Williamsburg; poems to Waller from Henry Wood and C[olley] Cibber, Jr.; and insurance policies for the property of the George Blacknall family in Norfolk, Va.
Also, a printed sermon preached by the Rev. John Camm, president of the College of William and Mary, on the death of [William Nelson], [1772?]; and a plan of Richard Blow's home, with genealogical information on the Blow family.
Arrangement
Chronologically arranged. Undated material placed at end.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Blow family.; Waller family.
Persons:
Backnall, Emma.; Backnall, George.; Blow, Richard.; Camm, John, 1718-1778 or 9.; Cibber, Colley, Jr.; Fry, Joshua, 1700 (ca.)-1754.; Nelson, William, 1711- 1772.; Page, Mann.; Waller, Benjamin, 1710- 1786.; Wood, Henry, 1696-1757.
Subjects:
Architecture--Virginia--Surry County--Designs and plans.; Justice, Administration of,--Virginia--James City County.; Insurance, Property--Virginia-- Norfolk.; Poetry, Modern--18th century.; Sermons, American.
Corporate Names:
Germania Fire Insurance Company of New York.; Globe Insurance Company.; Hanover Fire Insurance Company.; Liverpool and London Fire and Life Insurance Company.; Niagara Fire Insurance Company.; Phoenix Assurance.; Republic Fire Insurance Company.
Genre and Form Terms:
Insurance policies--Virginia--Norfolk--19th century.
Geographical Names:
Gloucester County (Va.)--Politics and government--18th century.; James City County (Va.)-- Politics and government--18th century.; Virginia--Genealogy.
Contents List
- Appointment, 26 October 1737. (Folder 1)
  Appointment of Benjamin Waller to be Register of the Court of Vice Admiralty in Virginia, signed by William Gooch. Colonies' seal attached.
- Appointment, 7 November 1737. (Folder 1)
  Appointment of Benjamin Waller, Deputy Clerk of James City County, signed by John Carter. Carter's red wax seal attached.
- Commission, 18 May 1738. (Oversize 1X)
  Gov. William Gooch appoints Benjamin Waller as King's Attorney in Gloucester.
- Commission, 4 December 1739. (Oversize 1X)
  Gov. William Gooch appoints Benjamin Waller as King's Attorney in James City County.
- Appointment, 10 December 1739. (Folder 1)
  Appointment of Benjamin Waller to be Clerk of the County of James City, signed by John Carter, Secretary of the Colony. Carter's red wax seal attached.
- Appointment, 10 December 1739. (Folder 1)
  Appointment of Benjamin Waller as Clerk of the Courts of Oyer and Terminer, signed by William Gooch.
- Appointment, 21 August 1740. (Folder 1)
  Appointment of Benjamin Waller as Clerk Assistant of the House of Burgesses, signed by William Gooch. Colonies' seal attached.
- Certificate, 21 August 1740. (Folder 1)
  A certificate, that the proper oaths have been administered to Benjamin Waller as Clerk Assistant of the House of Burgesses, signed by Philip Lightfoot and Thomas Lee.
- Certificate, 8 May 1742. (Folder 2)
  A certificate, that the proper oaths have been administered to Benjamin Waller, Clerk of the Committees of Propositions and Elections, signed by Cole Digges and John Tayloe.
- Appointment, 9 August 1742. (Oversize 1X)
  Appointment of Benjamin Waller as the Clerk of James City County, signed by John Robinson. Retains Robinson's red wax seal.
- Appointment, 9 April 1743. (Folder 2)
  Appointment of Benjamin Waller to be Clerk of the County of James City, signed by Thomas Nelson, Jr. Nelson's red wax seal attached.
- Articles of Agreement, 13 December 1743. (Oversize 1X)
  Articles of Agreement for the sale to Benjamin Waller by Mann Page, Gloucester Co., of 745 acres of land adjoining city of Williamsburg on the east, west, and north sides, formerly belonging to Elizabeth Bray. Retains Waller's red wax seal.
- Poem: "On the Death of Dr. [Edmund] Waller," [1745] (Folder 2)
  Waller was Doctor of Physick and a senior Fellow of John's College, Cambridge, who died in the year, 1745.
- Poem: "On the Death of Dr. Waller, design'd as an Apotheosis," [1745] (Folder 2)
  By Totton.
- Henry Wood to Benjamin Waller, 2 February 1745/6., ALS in verse. (Folder 2)
- C[olley] Cibber, Jr., to Benjamin Waller, 2 July 1746. (Folder 2)
  Informs Waller of his intention to visit him in Williamsburg while on his way to Boston from Charles-Town. Poems in Latin and English included.
- Poem: "Dear Brother Bard," 25 December 1752., 6 pages. (Folder 3)
  Written by Henry Wood.
- Henry Wood to Benjamin Waller, 4 December 1753. (Folder 3)
  Poem included.
- Henry Wood, Nelson Hill, to Benjamin Waller, 9 July 1754. (Folder 3)
- Henry Wood to Benjamin Waller, Williamsburg, ca. August 1754. (Folder 3)
  Mentions French and Indian War and also death of Joshua Fry.
- Letter from [George] Davenport to [Benjamin Waller], 30 November 1756. (Folder 3)
  Requests Mr. Waller to reconsider his resignation as Recorder of the City of Williamsburg. Signed by [George]Davenport.
- Song: "Whilst Damon whistles o'er the plain," 1759. (Folder 3)
  Appears as "Myrtilla to Damon" in Gentleman's Magazine, Vol. XXIX (May, 1759), pp. 228-229 by Mr. W[alle]r.
- Indenture, 5 April 1804. (Oversize 1X)
  Copy of an indenture: Mary M. Bennett, Norfolk, to George McIntosh, Norfolk, re lease of land on Norfolk's market square.
- James City County Court record, 8 October 1804. (Folder 4)
  Lists the claims of Jas. Taylor, Littleton Tazewell and Robert H. Waller for services they provided the county "relating to criminal prosecution." Signed by Robert H. Waller.
- Insurance policy, 14 October 1848., Printed form with manuscript insertions. (Oversize 1X)
  Insurance policy of Dr. George Blacknall of Norfolk, with the Phoenix Assurance Co. for property on Norfolk's Bute Street.
- Insurance policy, 1 December 1848., Printed form with manuscript insertions. (Oversize 1X)
- Insurance policy, 25 November 1865. (Oversize 1X)
  Insurance policy of Mrs. Emma Blacknall of Norfolk with The Germania Fire Insurance Company, The Hanover Fire Insurance Company, The Niagara Fire Insurance Company, and the Republic Fire Insurance Company for property at 90 W. Bute St., Norfolk.
- Deed, 6 April 1874., Printed form with manuscript insertions. (Oversize 1X)
  Deed between George McIntosh and Mary, his wife, of Norfolk, to Warren G. Elliot, for land on west side of Norfolk's market square deeded McIntosh by Emma Blacknall in 1874.
- Insurance policy, 9 February 1881., Printed form with manuscript insertions. (Oversize 1X)
  Insurance policy of Mrs. Emma Blacknall of Norfolk with Liverpool and London and Globe Ins. Co. for property at 132 Bute St.
- Insurance policy, 9 February 1911., Printed form with typed insertions. (Oversize 1X)
  Insurance policy of the estate of Mrs. Emma Blacknall with Liverpool and London and Globe Ins. Co. for property and furnishings at 286 Bute St.
- Insurance policy, 9 February 1912., Printed form with typed insertions. (Oversize 1X)
  Insurance policy of the estate of Mrs. Emma Blacknall, formerly of Norfolk, with Liverpool and London and Globe Ins. Co. for property at 286 Bute St.
- Receipt, 9 February 1912., Printed form with typed insertions. (Folder 4)
  Receipt for payment of insurance premiums. Estate of Mrs. Emma Blacknall, deceased, and Miss Emma Blacknall from George. W. Dey and Sons, Norfolk.
- Henry Wood to Benjamin Waller, ca. 1754. (Folder 5)
  The first part of the letter concerns the preparations for the trial of Tho. Abery, a horse thief. The letter also discusses the health of Wood's family.
- House plan. (Folder 5)
  Plan of home and garden of Richard Blow on Crawford Street overlooking Elizabeth River in Sussex, now Surry, Co. "Luty (?) Wallers pedigree" on verso of plan.
- Sermon, [1772?], 20 pages. (Folder 6)
  Printed sermon (20 pp.) preached by the Reverend John Camm, president of William and Mary College, for funeral of Mr. [William?] Nelson, p. 17 references "Mr. Nelson."